Guide to the Jay B. Hubbell Papers, 1816-1998 and undated, bulk 1920-1979 RL.00581
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings and Speeches Series, 1867-1998 and undated, bulk 1920-1979
  - Writings by Hubbell Subseries, 1908-1978 and undated, bulk 1920-1978
    This subseries contains original writings by Hubbell, both published and unpublished. It is divided into three sections: Manuscripts, A-Z; Publications Files; and Printed Materials. Manuscripts of lectures, articles, student handbooks, conference and meeting papers, and reminiscences written by Hubbell of literary figures and critics (including Frank Clyde Brown, Robert Frost, Lewis Leary, John H. McGinnis, and Carl Sandburg) can be found in the Manuscripts, A-Z folders. Reminiscences are filed alphabetically by the subject's last name. The Publications Files mainly consist of correspondence and related bureaucratic materials concerning Hubbell's published works, and are arranged alphabetically by title. An exception is the inclusion of a copy of his memoir of his wife, Lucinda. The Printed Materials files include reprints of Hubbell's articles and essays as well as reprints of reviews of his writings. The files also include a scrapbook in which reprints and clippings of newspaper articles, Hubbell's writings, and reviews of Hubbell's writings can be found. Folders arranged in alphabetical order by folder title.
    - Manuscripts, A-U, 1908-1978 and undated, 9 folders (Box 9)
    - Manuscripts, V-Z, 1908-1978 and undated, 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Publications Files, 1921-1977
      - American Life in Literature, 1932-1972 and undated
        - First Edition, 1932-1972 and undated (Box 10)
        - Revised Editions, 1947-1948 and undated (Box 10)
      - Eight American Authors, 1970-1976 and undated (Box 10)
      - The Enjoyment of Literature, 1929-1930 (Box 10)
      - Essays on American Literature in Honor of Jay B. Hubbell, 1966-1968 and undated (Box 10)
      - Introduction to Drama, 1926-1949 (Box 10)
      - Introduction to Poetry, 1921-1936 and undated (Box 10)
      - The Last Years of Henry Timrod, 1940-1945 (Box 10)
      - Lucinda, 1975-1977 (Box 10)
      - South and Southwest, 1965-1967 and undated (Box 10)
      - The South in American Literature
        - Correspondence and Clippings, 1954-1970 and undated (Box 10)
        - Reviews, 1954-1959 and undated (Box 11)
      - Southern Life in Fiction, 1960-1974 (Box 11)
      - Who Are the Major American Writers?
        - Correspondence and Notes, 1921-1974 and undated (Box 11)
        - Clippings, 1971-1975 (Box 11)
    - Printed Materials, 1921-1978 and undated
      - Articles, A-Z, 6 folders (Box 11)
      - Reviews (Box 12)
      - Scrapbook (Box 12)
  - Writings by Others Subseries, 1867-1998 and undated, bulk 1914-1979
    Contains many reprints inscribed and sent to Hubbell as well as articles and essays which Hubbell gathered, including copies of four pre-1900 essays. Several manuscripts of memoirs of early teachers of American literature written by their colleagues appear in these folders, filed by author's last name (memoirs also appear in the Writings by Hubbell and Correspondence, Alphabetical Series). Eleanor Marguerite Tilton's collected writings by and about Ralph Leslie Rusk are filed under her name, along with her reminiscence of Rusk. Items are arranged alphabetically by author's name.
    - Allen, Gay Wilson, 1937 (Box 12)
    - Anderson, Carl Lennart, 1971 (Box 12)
    - Author unknown, 1869 (Box 12)
    - Author unknown, 1887 (Box 12)
    - Basler, Roy Prentice, 1938-1977 and undated (Box 12)
    - Bernbaum, Ernest, 1926 (Box 12)
    - Blackstock, Walter, 1948 and undated (Box 12)
    - Blair, Walter, 1976 (Box 12)
    - Brown, Herbert Ross, 1935 (Box 12)
    - Bruccoli, Matthew Joseph, 1951-1978 (Box 12)
    - Cahill, William and Molly McKaughan, 1976 (Box 12)
    - Calhoun, Richard James, 1977 (Box 12)
    - Campbell, Harry Modean, 1954 (Box 12)
    - Canby, Henry Seidel, 1929 (Box 12)
    - Cannon, James and Lewis Patton, 1950 (Box 12)
    - Contrell, Clyde Hull, 1960 (Box 12)
    - Carlock, Mary Sue, undated (Box 12)
    - Centing, Richard R., 1978 (Box 12)
    - Chapman, John S., 1978 (Box 12)
    - Clark, Linda, 1980 (Box 12)
    - Cone, Eddie Gay, 1977-1985 (Box 12)
    - Davis, Arthur Kyle, 1972 (Box 12)
    - Davis, Curtis Carroll, 1970-1972 (Box 12)
    - Davis, Richard Beale, 1943-1978 (Box 12)
    - Day, George Parmly, 1914 (Box 12)
    - Duggan, Margaret, 1979 (Box 12)
    - Eidson, John Olin, 1956-1977 and undated (Box 12)
    - Fabian, Bernhard, 1959 (Box 12)
    - Ferguson, Oliver Watkins, 1971 (Box 12)
    - Fisher, Benjamin Franklin, 1971-1974 (Box 12)
    - Fisher, John Hurt, 1952-1955 (Box 12)
    - French, L. Virginia, 1868 (Box 12)
    - Fuson, Ben W., 1952 (Box 12)
    - Gates, William Bryan, 1960 (Box 12)
    - Gilbert, Allan H., 1954 (Box 12)
    - Gilbert, Katharine, 1949 (Box 12)
    - Gillis, Everett A., 1954 (Box 12)
    - Gohdes, Clarence L. F., 1936-1972 (Box 12)
    - Grattan, Clinton Hartley, 1931 (Box 12)
    - Gregory, S., 1871 (Box 12)
    - Gross, Theodore L., 1968-1978 (Box 12)
    - Guilds, John C., 1956-1960 (Box 12)
    - Hayne, Paul H., 1874 (Box 12)
    - Herron, Ima Honaker, 1960-1976 (Box 12)
    - Holman, Clarence Hugh, 1949-1950 (Box 12)
    - Holman, Harriet R., 1977 (Box 13)
    - Hornberger, Theodore, 1941 (Box 13)
    - Jackson, David Kelly, 1975-1976 (Box 13)
    - Jones, Howard Mumford, 1936-1956 (Box 13)
    - Kahn, Sholom Jacob, 1957 and undated (Box 13)
    - King, Robert T., 1977 (Box 13)
    - Kinnamon, Keneth, 1959 (Box 13)
    - Lampson, Robin, 1939-1940 (Box 13)
    - Law, Robert Adger, 1937 (Box 13)
    - Lawrence, David Herbert, 1926 (Box 13)
    - Lewis, John Smith, 1941 (Box 13)
    - Leary, Lewis Gaston, 1941-1976 (Box 13)
    - Mabbott, Maureen (Cobb), 1970-1980 (Box 13)
    - McCain, John Walker, 1970 (Box 13)
    - McDavid, Raven Ioor, 1972 (Box 13)
    - McDowell, Tremaine, 1930 (Box 13)
    - McKeithan, Daniel Morley, 1930-1979 (Box 13)
    - MacLeish, Archibald, 1976 (Box 13)
    - Markham, Edwin, undated (Box 13)
    - Miller, Perry, 1964 (Box 13)
    - Moore, Rayburn Sabatzky, 1954-1976 (Box 13)
    - Nakamura, Junichi, undated (Box 13)
    - Negley, Glenn, 1966 (Box 13)
    - Paton, Alan, 1959 (Box 13)
    - Pattee, Fred Lewis, 1924 and undated (Box 13)
    - Pfaff, Daniel Wayne, 1977 (Box 13)
    - Pierson, George Wilson, 1954 (Box 13)
    - Pound, Louise, 1942 (Box 13)
    - Raetz, Martha and M. Kahn, 1975 (Box 13)
    - Ralls, J. R., 1867 (Box 13)
    - Reece, James B., 1975 (Box 13)
    - Robert, Joseph Clarke, 1964-1972 (Box 13)
    - Roppolo, Joseph Patrick, 1956 (Box 13)
    - Rosenthal, Macha Louis, 1966-1974 (Box 13)
    - Rusk, Ralph Leslie, 1953 (Box 13)
    - Sanders, Charles Richard, 1957 (Box 13)
    - Shepperson, Archibald Bolling, 1954 (Box 13)
    - Shryock, Richard Harrison, 1940 (Box 13)
    - Smith, Henry Nash, 1975 (Box 13)
    - Smith, William Jay, 1976 (Box 14)
    - Stewart, Randall, 1955 (Box 14)
    - Spiller, Robert Ernest, 1967 (Box 14)
    - Stone, Edward, 1961-1966 (Box 14)
    - Stovall, Floyd, 1938 (Box 14)
    - Thompson, Edgar Tristam, 1965-1976 (Box 14)
    - Thorpe, James, 1974 (Box 14)
    - Tilton, Eleanor Marguerite, 1958-1979
      - Writings by Tilton, 1958 (Box 14)
      - Writings on Ralph Rusk, 1979, 6 folders (Box 14)
    - Tinker, Chauncey Brewster, 1974 (reprint of 1924 article) (Box 14)
    - Turner, Arlin, 1974 (Box 14)
    - Wells, Henry Willis, 1976 (Box 14)
    - Welty, Eudora, 1956 (Box 14)
    - White, George Abbott, 1978 (Box 14)
    - Wiesepape, Betty Holland, 1998 (Box 14)
    - Wiggins, Robert Lemuel, 1955 (Box 14)
    - Williams, Stanley Thomas, 1925 (Box 14)
    - Zeek, Charles Franklyn, 1953-1955 (Box 14)
    - Pamphlets and short writings, 1883-1966 and undated (Box 14)
- Subject Files Series, 1916-1980 and undated
  Includes material pertaining to the major events, institutions, and interests of Hubbell's life and career. Two subseries make up this series: General Files and Projects. Some material related to these subject files is filed elsewhere in the collection, in particular letters from Hubbell's more regular correspondents that appear in the Correspondence, Alphabetical Series. Papers concerning institutional appointments also can be found throughout the Correspondence and Biographical Data Series.
  - General Files Subseries, circa 1922-1980 and undated
    Contains materials on a broad range of topics: Hubbell's institutional affiliations (Southern Methodist University, Columbia, Clemson, and the University of Richmond), the proceedings of the Modern Language Association (MLA) and its American Literature Section, the Jay B. Hubbell Medallion (given by the MLA to honor American literary scholarship) and the Mayflower Award (given annually to the best nonfiction work by a North Carolina resident). Other areas of professional interest and concern, such as graduate students and courses, Duke Library collection development, and folklore make up the rest of the series. Items are filed alphabetically within the subseries and chronologically within each folder.
    - American Literature, 1969 (Box 14)
    - Clemson College, 1956-1961 and undated (Box 14)
    - Collection Development, 1961 and undated (Box 14)
    - Columbia University, 1957-1975 (Box 14)
    - Courses, 1954-1955 and undated (Box 14)
    - Duke University Press, undated (Box 14)
    - Eugenia Dorothy Blount Lamar Lectures, 1959 (Box 14)
    - Folklore, 1968-1976 (Box 14)
    - Graduate Studies, 1949 and undated (Box 14)
    - Jamestown, 1957 and undated (Box 15)
    - Jay B. Hubbell Center for Literary Historiography, 1976-1980 (Box 15)
    - Jay B. Hubbell Medallion, 1965-1976 (Box 15)
    - Mayflower Cup Award, 1955 (Box 15)
    - Modern Language Association of America, 1923-1977
      - Correspondence, 1927-1977, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Programs, 1926-1957 (Box 15)
    - Modern Language Association of America, American Literature Section, 1923-1977
      - Correspondence, 1923-1976 (Box 15)
      - Annual Reports, 1951-1977, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Modern Language Association of America, Comparative Language Section, 1948 (Box 15)
    - News Items, 1924-1978 and undated (Box 15)
    - Notes, circa 1922-1976 and undated (Box 15)
    - Phi Beta Kappa, circa 1961 (Box 15)
    - South Atlantic Modern Language Association, 1930-1954, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Southern Methodist University, 1951-1974 (Box 15)
    - Southwest Review, 1924-1970 (Box 15)
    - University of Richmond, 1929-1979, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Projects Subseries, 1916-1976 and undated
    Hubbell's interest in the development of literary scholarship, particularly of American and Southern literature, prompted him to undertake many projects throughout his career. One such project concerned Hubbell's role as an active contributor to the development of Duke University Library's literary collections. His interest in building a renowned collection of American literature and American literary scholarship at Duke is demonstrated throughout his papers, but most specifically in his proposal for the establishment of a Center for Southern Studies, whose purpose would be to house a vast historical and literary collection pertaining to the South. This plan never materialized as Hubbell envisioned in the letters that can be found in the "Center for Southern Studies" folders. In 1966, a Center for Southern Studies did open at Duke, but it was one in which Hubbell was not involved and whose vision Hubbell did not endorse.
    Similarly, Hubbell spearheaded the Cooperative Training Program for Foreign Teachers of American Literature initiative. Two universities, at first Harvard and Duke and then Minnesota and Duke, were to cooperatively implement a program to train instructors to teach American Literature abroad. Due to a lack of funding, the program was never begun. Another project which experienced financial setbacks was Hubbell's plan to compile a checklist of American literature manuscript sources in the United States. Hubbell introduced the idea in 1930 and participated in many negotiations over the project, but it was sidetracked because of insufficient funding. The 1960 publication of American Literary Manuscripts, however, completed the project that Hubbell had initiated 30 years earlier. Papers relating to this publication are in the J. A. Robbins Papers and American Literary Manuscripts Papers in the Hubbell Center at Duke University.
    This subseries also contains records of other more immediately successful projects, such as the SMU poetry contests, Correspondence Teaching, and the Extension Program at SMU. All files are alphabetical, and arranged chronologically by date within each folder.
    - Center for Southern Studies, 1929-1976 and undated (Box 16)
    - Checklist of Manuscripts, 1929-1976, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Correspondence Teaching, undated (Box 16)
    - Cooperative Training Program, 1951-1976 and undated (Box 16)
    - Extension Teaching, 1916-1950 (Box 16)
    - Revision of Cambridge History of American Literature, 1976 and undated. (Box 16)
    - Southern Methodist University Poetry Contests, 1922-1926 (Box 16)
    - Society for the Study of Southern Literature, circa 1967-1975 (Box 16)
- Teaching Abroad Series, 1948-1957 and undated
  Hubbell's many different teaching experiences included appointments at three universities outside of the United States. Hubbell served twice as Expert to the Secretary of the U. S. Army and Visiting Professor of American Literature at the University of Vienna. Reports which Hubbell submitted to the Army detailing his experiences can be found in the "Vienna" folders. The "Jerusalem" folders contain materials about Hubbell's brief trip to Israel. His appointment as Professor at Hebrew University was abridged as Hubbell and his wife were evacuated eight days after their arrival due to the outbreak of the Arab-Israeli conflict. This series also includes information about his teaching at the University of Athens. Additional accounts of his experience teaching abroad can be found in his writings, Lucinda and South and Southwest. Correspondence and materials about Hubbell's teaching within the United States appears throughout several series: Biographical Data, Correspondence, and Subject Files. Files are arranged alphabetically by location.
  - Athens (1953), 1952-1956 (Box 16)
  - Jerusalem (1956), 1956-1957 and undated, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Vienna (1949), 1948-1949 and undated (Box 17)
  - Vienna (1950), 1949-1950 and undated, 2 folders (Box 17)
- Photographs Series, 1861-1978 and undated
  The highlights of the Photographs Series include pictures of Hubbell throughout his life, including ones with his wife and young sons, and as a young Lieutenant; of colleagues, including a photograph of Hubbell's 90th birthday with many of his fellow Duke faculty; of the Hubbell's Pinecrest Rd., Durham home; of Carl Sandburg; and various other pictures of family, friends, and associates. The series contains black and white and color photographs, as well as candid pictures and formal portraits. The earliest photograph depicts Hubbell's relatives in uniform as Virginia Sharpshooters in the Civil War.
  - Photographs, 1861-1978 and undated; 2 folders (Box 17)
- Clippings Series, 1816-1984 and undated, bulk 1920-1969
  This series houses clippings of the many noteworthy personal and professional events of Hubbell's life, as well as clippings about contemporary events and Hubbell's friends and colleagues. While many clippings are scattered throughout the collection, this series contains those which were not originally filed by subject or correspondent. All personal clippings are housed in box 17, as the oversize folder of clippings only contains items relating to Hubbell's professional life.
  The oversize clippings folder contains newspaper articles written by Hubbell and articles written by others about his scholarly work. Articles include several authored by Hubbell in the Dallas Morning News from 1920, 1924, 1926, and 1927. Many clippings review Hubbell's writings and projects, including American Literature; The South in American Fiction, 1607-1900; South and Southwest; and Essays on American Literature in Honor of Jay B. Hubbell. Other subjects include the SMU poetry contests and winners, John Lomax's folksong collections, the University of Richmond's 100th Anniversary newspaper (1932), and a Viennese paper's announcement of Hubbell's visiting professorship. All clippings are arranged chronologically by date.
  - Clippings, 1816-1984 and undated, bulk 1950-1969, 5 folders (Box 17)
- Oversize Material
  - Clippings Series (Folder 1, 3)
    - Clippings, 1920-1974 and undated (Box 17)
  - Subject Files Series (Folder 2)
    - Southern Methodist University, 1974 (Box 17)